Beschrijving van de collection Cornelis Hendrik van Schooneveld
Universiteitsbibliotheek Leiden
- Archives regarding Mouton and related activities (inv. nos. 1-13)., A.
  - Correspondence about reprints., 4.; Correspondence about reprints which appeared in the series Slavistic printings and reprintings.; 1 box.; The Europe Printing company of H. Francl in Vaduz (Liechtenstein) provided reprints of Russian books, which were published in the above named series. These
    - Printing orders., Correspondence on Russian reprints which appeared in the series Slavistic printings and reprintings.
      20. Buslaev, F. (Istoričeskie očerki russkoj…).
      21. (Carskaja diplomatija i Parižskaja kommuna v 1871... ).
      22. (Carskaja Rossija v mirovoj vojne.)
      23. Čečulin, N.D. (Goroda Moskovskogo gosudarstva).
      24. Charlampovič, K.V. (Malorossijskoe vlijanie na...).
      25. (Dejateli revoljucionnogo dviženija v Rossii.)
      26. (Dejateli Sojuza Sov. Soc...)
      27. (Delo Petraščevcev.).
      28. D’jakonov, M.M. (Očerki iz istorii sel’skogo…).
      29. D’jakonov, M.M. (Vlast’ moskovskich gosudarej…).
      30. Dragomanov, M.A. (Pis’ma M.A. Bakunina...).
      31. (Ènciklopedija gosudarstva i prava.).
      32. (Ežegodnik Leninskoj i...).
      33. Gagarin, J.X. (Les jésuites de Russie).
      34. Garkavi, A.J. (Skazanija musul’manskich pisatelej...).
      35. Gennadi, G.N. (Spravočnyj slovar’…).
      36. Geršenzon, M.O. (P.Ja. Čaadaev).
      37. Gogol’, N.V.
      38. Grossman, L.P.
      39. Haumant, E. (La culture française en Russie…).
      40. Ikonnikov, V.S. (Opyt issledovanija o kul’turnom...).
      41. (Južno-russkie rabočie sojuzy...).
      42. Ključevskij, V.O. (Drevnerusskie žitija svjatych…).
      43. Kokorev, A.V. (Chrestomatija po russkoj literature…).
      44. Kokovcov, V.N. (Iz moego prošlogo).
      45. Kornilov, A. (Kurs istorii Rossii…).
      46. Koz’min, B. (P.N. Tkačev i revoljucennoe...).
      47. Kropotkin, P.A.
      48. Kušelev-Bezborodko, G.I. (Pamjatniki...).
      49. Lamzdorf, V.N.
      50. (Legal’naja social-demokratičeskaja...).
      51. (Leniniana.).
      52. (Lenskie sobytija 1912 goda.).
      53. Leont’ev, A.A. (Vostok, Rossija i Slavjanstvo).
      54. (Materialy dlja biografičeskogo slovarja...)
      55. (Materialy dlja biografii M. Bakunina.).
      56. (Materaly k istorii krest’janskogo revoljucionnogo...).
      57. (Meždunarodnye otnošenija v... Serija 2 vols. 18, 19, 20.).
      58. (Meždunarodnye otnošenija v... Serija 3 Vols. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10.).
      59. Milonov, Ju. (Putevoditel’ po...).
      60. (Monarchija pered krušeniem...)
      61. Naščokin, V.A.(Zapiski).
      62. (Nečaev i nečaevcy. Političeskie...).
      63. vacant.
      64. (Novgorodskie piscovye knigi.).
      65. Orlov, A.S. (Vladimir Monomach).
      66. Ovsjaniko-Kulikovskij, D.N. (Istorija russkoj literatury).
      67. Ovsjaniko-Kulikovskij, D.N. (Sobranie sočinenij).
      68. (Perepiska Nikolaja i Aleksandry.).
      69. (Perepiska Vilgel’ma II s Nikolaem II.).
      70. vacant.
      71. Peretc, V.N. (Kratkij očerk metodologii istorii russkoj literatury).
      72. (Pervaja russkaja revoljucija.).
      73. (Pervoe marta 1887 g…).
      74. (Pis’ma Pobedonosceva.).
      75. Plotkin, L.A. (Pisarev i…).
      76. (Pokušenie Karakozova.).
      77. (Političeskie processy.).
      78. Puškin, A.S.
      79. (Puškin i ego sovremenniki.).
      80. (Putilovec v 3-ch revoljucijach.).
      81. Pypin, A.N. (Istorija russkoj literatury).
      82. Radimova, S. (Ukazatel’ professional’noj literatury…).
      83. (Russkaja podpol’naja i zarubežnaja pečat’…).
      84. Tichonravov, N.S. (Russkie byliny…).
      85. (Russko-germanskie otnošenija…).
      86. Šachmatov, A.A. (Očerk sovremennogo russkogo…).
      87. Šachmatov, A.A. (Povest’ vremennych let).
      88. Savva, V.I. (Moskovskie cari…).
      89. Seliščev, A.M. (Slavjanskoe jazykoznanie).
      90. Šilov, A.A.
      91. Šklovskij, E.B.
      92. Šklovskij, E.B. (Chudožestvennaja proza).
      93. Social-demokratičeskie listovki.
      94. Speranskij, M.N. (Russkaja ustnaja slovesnost’…).
      95. (Stački 1881-1885 gg.).
      96. Suchomlinov, M.I. (Issledovanija po russkoj literature…).
      97. Tolstoj, L.N. (Anna Karenina).
      98. Tomaševskij, B.V.
      99. (Učastniki russkogo revoljucionnogo…).
      100. (Vol’naja russkaja pečat’ v Rossijskoj.).
      101. (Vospominanija L’va Tichomirova.).
      102. (Vosstanie dekabristov).
  - Telex messages from and to Bloomington., 5.; Telex messages from 1969-1974.; 5 boxes.; Van Schooneveld had use of a telex machine at his private address in Bloomington for his contacts with Mouton. The messages extant have almost exclusively been sent to Mouton, The Hague, and to Vozérier-Amancy, France, where Van Schooneveld had another telex machine since 1971 (see Inv.No. 6).
    1. 1969.
    2. Summer 1970.
    3. Fall 1970.
    4. Through December 31, 1970.
    5. 1970.
    6. 1970-1971.
    7. May 1, 1971- September 30, 1971.
    8. June 10, 1971-December 31, 1971.
    9. 1971.
    10. October 4, 1971 - May 30, 1972.
    11. June 1972 - December 1972.
    12. Jan 17, 1972 -.
    13. Summer 1972.
    14. September 1972- December 1972.
    15. August 1972-January 1973.
    16. January 1973 - August 1973.
    17. January 1973 - May 1973.
    18. Fall 1973 (1).
    19. Fall 1973 (2).
    20. June 1973 - December 1973.
    21. January 1974 - March 1974.
    22. April 1974 - June 1974.
    23. July 1974 - August 1974.
    24. 1974 (1).
    25. 1974 (2).
  - Telex messages from and to Vozerier-Amancy., 6.; Telex messages from 1971-1974.; 2 boxes.; Van Schooneveld had, for his contacts with Mouton, the use of a telex machine at his vacation house in Vozérier-Amancy, france, in addition to the one at his private address in Bloomington (see Inv.No. 5). In those years there was telex traffic not only between France and The Hague, but also between France and Bloomington, where the staff of Van Schooneveld's department at Indiana University handled the telex traffic.
    1. 1971.
    2. 1971-1972.
    3. 1972.
    4. 1973.
    5. Summer 1973.
    6. August 1973-December 1973.
    7. Travel file.
    8. 1974.
    9. Telex file for Vozérier.
  - Various Mouton files., 7.; Correspondence and other items regarding Mouton publishers.; 13 boxes.; The items are ordered by subject. One can find general items about the series that were edited by Van Schooneveld: production schedules, copyright information, annual reports, brochures and catalogues, correspondence between Van Schooneveld and lawyers regarding legal questions, items about financial business, such as declarations and royalties. Added to this are the 'royalty statements' of the Walter de Gruyter & Co. publishing company, which specify by title and year the sale of each volume from Van Schooneveld's series. Mouton & Co. was sold to Walter de Guyter & Co. in 1977.
    - Files concerning the three series edited by C.H. van Schooneveld.
      1. Contracts.
      2. Slavistic printings and reprintings (SPR).
      3. SPR: Series didactica.
      4. SPR: Cancels of orders.
      5. SPR: Style-sheets.
      6. SPR: Dissertation abstracts.
      7. SPR: Francl reprint file.
      8. SPR: Suggested reprints.
      9. vacant.
      10. SPR: Reprint ideas: general.
      11. Janua linguarum (JL).
      12. JL: Series sovietica.
      13. JL: Series anastatica.
      14. JL: Series practica.
      15. JL: Pragensis.
      16. JL: Series critica (W. Winter, ed.).
      17. JL: Dissertation abstracts accepted.
      18. De Proprietatibus litterarum (DPL).
      19. DPL: Series textologica.
      20. DPL: Reprints.
      21. DPL: Style-sheet.
      22. DPL: Dissertation abstracts accepted.
    - Manuscripts.
      23. Manuscripts in groups & pouches before 1968.
      24. Manuscripts in groups & pouches 1968 and 1969.
      25. Inventory 'in-consideration' file summer 1970.
      26. Manuscripts rejected by Mouton 1974.
      27. Dissertation abstracts.
      28. Abstract lists & replys before 1966.
      29. Abstract lists & replys 1966.
      30. Abstract lists & replys 1967.
      31. Abstract lists & replys 1968.
      32. Dissertation abstracts solicited from Vozérier summer 1970.
      33. Dissertation abstracts: Rejections.
      34. Editorial meeting.
      35. Complaints.
      36. Manuscript evaluation forms.
      37. Publication procedures.
      38. Form letters.
      39. Draft-agreement (sample).
    - Other Mouton projects.
      40. Approaches to semiotics (Sebeok, ed.).
      41. Chinese linguistics.
      42. 'Collected articles' sollicitations, July 16, 1978.
      43. Conference center proposal (France): Guiraud - Sebeok.
      44. Current trends in linguistics (ed. Thomas A. Sebeok).
      45. Current trends in the language sciences.
      46. Encyclopedia of Philosophy.
      47. The Facts of Literature.
      48. French Foreign project.
      49. Greimas project.
      50. Indiana Slavic Studies.
      51. International Journal of Oriental Languages.
      52. Kultura (Budapest).
      53. Languages of India.
      54. Linguistic interviews.
      55. Linguistics (journal).
      56. Linguistics in the Netherlands.
      57. Literary Theory.
      58. van Loon: World Anthropology.
      59. Manuscript reprint proposal.
      60. Russian formalist writings (T. Sebeok).
      61. Stanford Studies in Germanics and Slavics.
      62. Tax, Sol: President, 1973 World Anthropology Congress at Chicago.
      63. Texas Institute.
    - Financial matters.
      64. Mouton royalty statements and other financial specifics 1955-1957.
      65. Mouton royalty statements and other financial specifics 1958-1959.
      66. Mouton royalty statements and other financial specifics 1960-1962.
      67. Mouton royalty statements and other financial specifics 1963.
      68. Mouton royalty statements and other financial specifics 1964.
      69. Mouton royalty statements and other financial specifics 1965-1966.
      70. Mouton royalty statements and other financial specifics 1966.
      71. Mouton royalty statements and other financial specifics 1967.
      72. Mouton royalty statements and other financial specifics 1968.
      73. Mouton (Europe Printing) reprint figures 1968-1969.
      74. Mouton royalty statements and other financial specifics 1969.
      75. Mouton royalty statements and other financial specifics 1970.
      76. Mouton royalty statements and other financial specifics 1971.
      77. Mouton financial copies for Vozérier 1970-1971.
      78. Mouton royalty statements and other financial specifics 1972.
      79. Mouton royalty statements and other financial specifics 1973-1976.
      80. Finance file, March 1974-.
      81. Mouton royalty statements and other financial specifics 1974.
      82. Mouton royalty statements and other financial specifics 1975.
      83. Mouton royalty statements and other financial specifics 1976.
      84. Finance file: general.
      85. Mouton publishers and antiquarian booksellers: invoices for C.H. van Schooneveld.
      86. Mouton Expense account.
      87. Mouton Expense account: checks.
      88. Mouton Expense account: check registers.
      89. Mouton Expense account: deposit tickets.
      90. Mouton Expense account: credit invoices.
      91. Walter de Gruyter royalty statements 1977.
      92. Walter de Gruyter royalty statements 1978.
      93. Walter de Gruyter royalty statements 1979.
      94. Walter de Gruyter royalty statements 1980.
      95. Walter de Gruyter royalty statements 1981.
      96. Walter de Gruyter royalty statements 1982.
      97. Walter de Gruyter royalty statements 1983.
      98. Walter de Gruyter royalty statements 1984.
      99. Walter de Gruyter royalty statements 1985.
      100. Walter de Gruyter royalty statements 1986.
      101. Walter de Gruyter royalty statements 1987.
      102. Walter de Gruyter royalty statements 1988.
      103. Walter de Gruyter royalty statements 1989.
      104. Walter de Gruyter royalty statements 1990.
      105. Walter de Gruyter royalty statements 1991.
      106. Walter de Gruyter royalty statements 1992.
      107. Walter de Gruyter royalty statements 1993.
      108. Walter de Gruyter royalty statements 1994.
      109. Walter de Gruyter royalty statements 1995.
      110. Walter de Gruyter royalty statements 1996.
      111. Walter de Gruyter royalty statements 1997.
      112. Walter de Gruyter royalty statements 1998.
      113. Walter de Gruyter royalty statements 1999.
    - Legal matters.
      114. Correspondence with Geelkerken & Linkens, solicitor's office in Leiden.
      115. Copyright information.
      116. Soviet copyright convention.
      117. Mouton Research Company.
      118. Manuscript insurance.
    - Various Mouton files.
      119. American secretary 1966.
      120. Blank forms.
      121. Book inventory: C.H.v.S copies.
      122. Books stored in Nuenen (December 1973).
      123. Books stored in Nuenen (October 1975).
      124. Notes and useful information on office procedures.
      125. Boris Pasternak (1958).
      126. Possev-Verlag.
      127. Production schedule.
      128. Teletype.
    - Annual reports and flyers.
      129. Mouton annual reports (1966, 1968, 1969).
      130. Merger announcement of Van Goor and Mouton.
      131. Edicom annual reports (1970, 1971, 1972, 1974).
      132. Flyers concerning the three series edited by C.H.van S.
      133. Other Mouton flyers.
      134. Mouton de Gruyter flyers.
  - Manuscripts., 8.; Manuscripts (typescripts, photocopies or proofs), in alphabetical order by author's name, that were sent to Van Schooneveld for publication in one of his series.; 21 boxes.
    1. Altman, M. (Reading Tolstoy).
    2. Bar-Adon, A. (The rise and decline of a dialect: a study in the revival of modern Hebrew).
    3. Barrack, C.M. (A diachronic phonology from Proto-Germanic to Old English stressing West-Saxon conditions).
    4. Bidwell, C.E. (Slavic historical phonology in tabular form).
    5. Birnbaum, H. (Problems of typological and genetic linguistics viewed in a generative framework).
    6. Borg, A. (Sound system of Maltese).
    7. Botha, R.P. (Methodological aspects of transformational generative phonology).
    8. Bradley, A.G. (Pastoral in the novels of George Eliot).
    9. Brutjan, G.A. (Princip lingvističeskoj dopolnitel'nosti versus Principa lingvističeskoj otnositel'nosti).
    10. Buehler, P.G. (Genesis and exodus: a running commentary).
    11. Carpenter, C.W. (The systematic exploitation of the verbal calque in German).
    12. Chayen, M.J. (Phonology of modern Hebrew).
    13. Christoff, P.K. (K.S. Aksakov).
    14. Cibulka, J.
    15. Čiževskij, D.-s16. Clifford, J. (Tense and Tense Logic).
    16. Clifford, John. (Tense and Tense Logic).
    17. Collinge, N.E. (The Indo-European laryngeal).
    18. Coseriu, E. (Synchrony, diachrony and typology).
    19. Culik, K. (Mathematical theory of languages).
    20. Culik, K. (Algebraic linguistics).
    21. Despalatovič, E.M. (Ljudovit Gaj and the Illyrian movement (to1843)).
    22. Dobin, E.S. (The nature of detail).
    23. Fox, A. (Prosody of the non-pentameter line).
    24. Fraenkel, G. (Linguistic bibliography of interlinguistics).
    25. Garvin, P.L. (Aspects of linguistic discovery).
    26. Garvin, P.L. (Discovery procedure: theory and practice and aspects of linguistic discovery).
    27. Heine, B. (Sprachsoziologische Probleme in Afrika).
    28. Herrfurth, H.
    29. Hopkins, W.H. (The development of 'pornographic' literature in eighteenth- and early nineteenth-century Russia).
    30. Humprey, N.D.
    31. Juilland, A., and A. Roceric (Word and language: a comprehensive anthology).
    32. Juilland, A., and A. Roceric (The decline of the word).
    33. Kacnel'son, S.D. (The typology of language and verbal-thought).
    34. Kittredge, R.I. (Test frames for English verbal aspect).
    35. Kramsky, J. (The word as a linguistic unit).
    36. Li, C.N. (A computerized bibliography on generative semantics and syntax).
    37. Liem, N. (Cases, clauses, and sentences in Vietnamese: a Vietnamese-English contrastive analysis).
    38. Marković, B. (Dostoevsky in England).
    39. Mayenowa, M.R. (Theoretical poetics: survey of linguistic problems).
    40. Meillet, A. (Selected works by and about).
    41. Mel'čuk, I.A. (Opyt teorii lingvističeskich modelej <smysl'-tekst> (semantika-sintaksis)).
    42. Moser, C. (Bulgarian literature).
    43. Munro, D.A. (Rewrite rules for psychology).
    44. Nash, R. (International interference in the speech of Puerto Rican bilinguals).
    45. Newman, R.S. (The tragedy of wit: transformations in Augustan Drama, 1660-1750).
    46. Oinas, F. (ed.) (The heroic epic).
    47. Ornstein, J. (Programmed instruction and educational technology in the language teaching field: new approaches to old problems).
    48. Osgood, C.E. (Focus on meaning: psycholinguistic papers).
    49. Ozerov, N. (Sinajskij Paterik: its orthography, and date and place of origin).
    50. Palková, Z.(The rhytmical potential of prose).
    51. Pashin, N. (Solženicyn.
    slovotvorec).
    52. Pelc, J. (Proper names in natural language: prolegomena to a theory).
    53. Pomorska, K. (Invariants and variables of Boris Pasternak).
    54. Pucci, P. (The poetic language and Hesiod).
    55. Rallides, C. (The tense aspect system of the Spanish verb).
    56. Rundzjo, K.H. (Surrealizm rosyjski).
    57. Schramm, G.M. (The non-finite forms of the verb).
    58. Shapiro, M. (Markedness and Russian stress).
    59. Shapiro, M. (Toward the recognition of iconicity in language).
    60. Sheldahl, T.K. (Foundations for a generalized theory of semantic description).
    61. Slama-Cazacu, T. (The dialogue in children).
    62. Sötér, I. (The dilemma of literary science).
    63. Takefuta, Y. (A study of American intonation I: development of the method of analysis).
    64. Tener, R.L. (The phoenix riddle: a study of irony in comedy).
    65. Tökei, F. (Genre theory in China in the 3rd-6th centuries).
    66. Unknown author.
    67. Unknown author.
    68. Unknown author.
    69. Vanek, A.L. (On some problems in the phonology of Czech conjugation).
    70. Vernier, R. ('Poésie ininterrompue' et la poétique de Paul Eduard).
    71. Voyles, J.B. (West Germanic inflection, derivation, and compounding).
    72. Waengler, H.-H., and J. Rosenbek.
    73. Waters, D.D. (The symbolic and structural role of Duessa in Book One of 'The Faerie Queene').
    74. Zierer, E.
    75. Zsilka, J. (Dialectics of the motion form in language).
  - Physsardt Publishers., 9.; Correspondence and other items regarding Physsardt Publishers.; 3 boxes.; Van Schooneveld ran Physsardt, a small publishing house in Bloomington (Indiana), that published a few books after De Ridder's departure from Mouton in 1974. Among these was Van Schooneveld's own 1978 work Semantic transmutations: prolegomena to a calculus of meaning. The files, particularly from 1976-1980, contain correspondence concerning these publications, and items on general organizational, legal and financial questions.
    - Editorial matters., Correspondence, in alphabetical order by name, concerning manuscripts that were earmarked for publication by Physsardt.
      2. Crapo, R.H. (Basic Quechua).
      3. England, B. (Glossarized charts of Noam Chomsky's grammar).
      4. Gardiner, D. (Intonation and music).
      5. Gartner, C.
      6. Jackson, R.L. (Dostoevsky's underground man in Russian literature).
      7. Jackson, R.L. (Dostoevsky's quest for form).
      8. Jacobs, M. (The partitive article in French … ).
      9. McLaws, Galina.
      10. Milner, M.R.
      11. Schooneveld, C.H. van (Semantic transmutations ...).
      12. Shepler, F.J. (Creatures from within: imagery being in the work of Henri Michaux).
      13. Stuart, D.G. ( Japanese Haiku of the school of Shiki).
    - Various files.
      14. Petr Aleksandrovič Kudrik 1966-1967.
      15. George Szwede 1967.
      16. Production 1968.
      17. Binding 1967-1968.
      18. Bulgakov 1970.
      19. Organization 1970.
      20. Physsardt 1971.
      21. Tax returns 1979.
      22. Yearly account statement 1981.
      23. Legal.
      24. Promotion.
      25. Orders.
      26. University reading lists.
      27. Signifié et signifiant.
  - Boy Tour Publishers, Geneva., 9B.; Correspondence, in chronological order, 1994-2002.; 1 box.; Van Schooneveld ran Boy Tour, a small publishing house nominally based in Geneva. It published three books in a restarted series Slavistic printings and reprintings (no. 1-3 (365-367)) edited by C.H. van Schooneveld. The files contain mostly correspondence with Ju.K. Begunov, the author of the three books published by Boy Tour (in the years 2000-2005). Other adressees are: Andrews, E. - Campen, J. van - Geelkerken & Linkens, solicitors - Gutiev, A. - Kollman, N.S. - Liapunov, V. - Uyterlinde, J. - Waszink, P.
    1. Correspondence, 1994.
    2. Correspondence, 1995.
    3. Correspondence, 1996.
    4. Correspondence, 1997.
    5. Correspondence, 1998.
    6, Correspondence, 1999.
    7. Correspondence, 2000.
    8. Correspondence, 2001.
    9. Correspondence, 2002.
  - The Peter de Ridder Press., 10.; correspondence and other items regarding The Peter de Ridder Press.; 1 box.; After leaving Mouton in 1974 Peter de Ridder began his own publishing company The Peter de Ridder Press in his hometown of Lisse. In this section are files ordered by subject, including contacts with the Bloomington Distribution Group (see Inv.No. 13), folders, and also some files on publication plans, in which Van Schooneveld was involved, the content of which resembles the Mouton editing files (see inv. no. 1).
    - Editorial matters., Correspondence, in alphabetical order by name, concerning manuscripts that were earmarked for publication by The Peter de Ridder Press.
      1. Abraham, W., and D.G. Stuart (Pieter Verburg Festschrift).
      2. Chardžiev, N.I. (Majakovskij i živopis').
      3. Chardžiev, N.I. (Kazimir Malevič).
      4. Chardžiev, N.I. (Opyt chudožnika novoj mery).
      5. Chardžiev, N.I. (Russkie kubo-futuristy).
      6. Mazzola, M.L. (Proto-Romance and Sicilian).
      7. Menges, K.H. (The Orient as reflected in the dawn of Slavic history).
      8. Rauch, I. (Herbert Penzl Festschrift).
      9. Soffietti, J.P. (Communication, meaning and language).
      10. Waugh, L.R. (Bolinger Festschrift).
      11. Worth, D.S. (A.V. Issatschenko Festschrift).
    - Other correspondence.
      12. Correspondence Peter de Ridder-C.H. van Schooneveld, 1974-1987.
    - Various files.
      13. Bloomington Distribution Group.
      14. Bloomington Translation Group.
      15. Index Current trends in linguistics.
      16. Flyers.
  - Bloomington Translation Group: translators., 11.; Correspondence concerning translation work, in alphabetical order by name of translator.; 4 boxes.; At the beginning of the 1970s, Van Schooneveld oversaw a group of free lance translators, the Bloomington Translation Group, that did translations (often from Russian to English) as Mouton publications required. These files contain correspondence with translators, usually conducted through the coordinator of these activities, Laurence Richter.